<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>med.io</title>
    <description>A blog of tables</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 16:02:25 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 16:02:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Antibiotics used for coverage of Pseudomonas aeruginosa</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P. aeruginosa&lt;/strong&gt; is a Gram-negative bacillus well-known for its blue-green pus and multiple mechanisms of drug resistance. It’s associated with several infections in the hospital setting such as ventilator-associated pneumonia, central venous catheter infection, UTIs, and surgical site infections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conditions that are prone to Pseudomonas infection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cystic fibrosis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Immunosuppression/neutropenia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Burns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diabetes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foreign bodies (e.g,vascular grafts, orthopedic implants)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general approach to treatment in cases of suspected Pseudomonas bacteremia/septicemia is to first start combination therapy with an &lt;em&gt;extended-spectrum beta-lactam and either an aminoglycoside or a fluoroquinolone&lt;/em&gt;. However, there is a trend towards &lt;strong&gt;monotherapy with piperacillin-tazobactam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; due to the nephrotoxicity associated with aminoglycosides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De-escalate (narrow) the antibiotic coverage once suspceptibility testing returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  Piperacillin is often combined with &lt;strong&gt;tazobactam&lt;/strong&gt; in order to overcome the beta-lactamases produced by Gram-negative bacteria. Tazobactam doesn’t add activity against pseudomonas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Ertapenem&lt;/em&gt; is a carbapenem that does NOT have antipseudomonal activity.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 22:42:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/drugs-against-pseudomonas</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/drugs-against-pseudomonas</guid>
        
        <category>pharmacology</category>
        
        <category>infectious disease</category>
        
        
        <category>Table</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drugs used for neuromuscular blockade during general anesthesia</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two classes of neuromuscular blocking drugs (NMBD) used as paralytic agents during the induction of general anesthesia–&lt;strong&gt;depolarizing&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;nondepolarizing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some reasons for using neuromuscular blockade in the OR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paralyze vocal cords and jaw muscules to allow for endotracheal intubation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paralyze respiratory muscles so that ventilation can be controlled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paralyze the abdominal muscles intraoperatively during abdominal or laparoscopic surgery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  NMBDs do not have analgesic or anesthetic effects and should always be given &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; the patient is sufficiency anesthetized
  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  Due to risk for &lt;strong&gt;acute hyperkalemia&lt;/strong&gt;, caution when giving succinylcholine to burn or trauma patients, and to children due to possible unrecognized muscular dystrophy.
  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sugammadex&lt;/strong&gt; is a newer drug that can be used for reversal of nondepolarizing NMBDs such as rocuronium. It basically encapsulates and inactivates the NMBD (very different from neostigmine) and has no effect at the neuromuscular junction&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2016 22:42:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/neuromuscular-blockade-drugs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/neuromuscular-blockade-drugs</guid>
        
        <category>pharmacology</category>
        
        <category>anesthesia</category>
        
        
        <category>Table</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Otitis externa versus acute otitis media</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Otitis externa (OE) and acute otitis media (AOM) share some similar clinical exam findings (otalgia, hearing loss, otorrhea); thus, the &lt;strong&gt;otoscopic&lt;/strong&gt; exam is important. OE is more likely to have external ear canal inflammation and erythema with a relatively benign TM, while AOM should show a bulging TM, effusion, perforation, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these entities may have complications and/or extension of the ear infection, i.e., to the mastoid, neck, or intracranially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment for OE is predominantly &lt;strong&gt;topical&lt;/strong&gt;, while treatment for AOM is usually &lt;strong&gt;oral&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 22:42:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/otitis-externa-versus-otitis-media</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/otitis-externa-versus-otitis-media</guid>
        
        <category>pediatrics</category>
        
        <category>pathology</category>
        
        <category>differential</category>
        
        
        <category>Table</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
